Finding aid to the Grounds Subject files CA.MS.00137
Smith College Archives
Grounds Subject files
1879-2010
Smith College Archives
Smith College.
CA.MS.00137
4.542 linear feet (12 containers)
1 website
The Grounds Subject Files contain information relating to the history, composition, and physical features of the Smith College Campus.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Grounds Subject Files were created by the various departments and donated to the College Archives.
Biographical / Historical
In 1892, plans designed by landscape architect Frederick Law Olmsted were adopted by President Seelye to turn the Smith College campus into a single large botanic garden, labeling all trees and shrub for aesthetic and educational purposes. Francis Ganong was appointed the first director of the botanic garden in 1894, and a systematics garden, based on the theories of Adolf Engler and Karl Prantl was added to the plan under his direction. The master plan has undergone numerous changes, including new systems of walkways and lawns, the expansion of the Lyman Plant House, the construction of a Japanese tea hut and garden, and the reorganization of the herbaceous garden according to more current evolutionary theories.
Related Material
Researchers should also view:
___22. Buildings Subject Files, Lyman Plant House
___Rolland and Towers Master Landscape Plan for Smith College
Scope and Contents
The Grounds Subject Files contain materials describing the history of the campus as a botanic garden and the changes to the master plan, lists of plantings and specimen placement, as well as information regarding the physical features of the campus, such as Paradise Pond, and structures and memorial pieces such as the Grecourt Gates and Lanning fountain. Types of materials include photographs, newspaper clippings, maps, pamphlets, lists, and letters.
- Athletic Fields
  - Allen Field #1 and Clubhouse, 1882-1981 (Box 263, Folder 1)
  - Allen Field #2-West St., 1922; 1956; undated (Box 263, Folder 2)
  - Field #3, 1993; 1965; undated (Box 263, Folder 3)
- Botanic Garden
  - General, 1895-1995 (Box 263, Folder 4)
  - Plant Collections and Specialty Gardens, 1974-1997 (Box 263, Folder 5)
  - Correspondences, 1892-1937 (Box 263, Folder 6)
  - Maps, 1895-1981 (Box 263, Folder 7)
  - Plant Collections and Specialty Gardens- Capen Garden, 1974-1999 (Box 263, Folder 8)
  - Plant Collections and Specialty Gardens- Rock Garden, 1925; 1991-1996 (Box 263, Folder 9)
  - Friends of the Botanic Garden, 1993-1996 (Box 263, Folder 10)
  - Outreach Programs, 1992- (Box 263, Folder 11)
  - Awards and Grants, 1992-2001 (Box 263, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, 1901-1994 (Box 263, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, 1904-1975 (Box 263, Folder 14)
  - Duplicates (Box 263, Folder 15)
  - Seed Lists, 1939; 1957-1959; 1962-1964; 1966-1967; 1973 (Box 263.1, Folder 1)
  - Plant Lists- Conifers and Herbs (Box 263.1, Folder 2)
  - Botanic Garden News - Publication, 1998-2002 (Box 263.1, Folder 3)
  - Botanic Garden News - Publication, 2003-2009 (Box 263.1, Folder 4)
  - Botanic Garden News - Publication, 2010- (Box 263.1, Folder 5)
  - Index Seminum, 1991/92-2001/02 (Box 263.1, Folder 6)
  - Index Seminum, 1975/76-1990/91 (Box 263.1, Folder 7)
  - Conservatory Restoration- Lyman Plant House, 2001 (Box 263.1, Folder 8)
  - Botanic Garden renovation and re-opening, 1981 October 9; 2018-A-0088; Elaine Chittenden; The Botanic Garden of Smith College; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 263.1, Folder 9, 6)
    Elaine Chittenden; The Botanic Garden of Smith College
  - Centennial Celebration: Scrapbook, 1995 (Box 263.2, Folder 1)
  - Centennial Celebration, 1995 (Box 263.2, Folder 2)
  - Botanic Gardens website, first captured 2019; 1 website
    Scope and Contents
    The Botanic Gardens of Smith College website (https://garden.smith.edu/) includes history and maps of the gardens gardens on campus, a plant collection database, news, events, exhibits, educational resources, student research projects, and electronic publications.
    Accruals
    The Botanic Gardens website was first captured in 2015 as part of the larger Smith College archived website. When the website was redesigned in January 2019 the domain name of the site changed and was captured separately. Subsequent captures are scheduled annually.
    Related Materials
    For earlier versions of the Botanic Gardens website see the Smith College website captured 2015-2018: href="https://wayback.archive-it.org/6152/*/https://www.smith.edu/"
- Arboretum Planting Plans
  - General Areas (Box 263.3, Folder 1)
  - Areas 1-5 (Box 263.3, Folder 2)
  - Areas 6-10 (Box 263.3, Folder 3)
  - Areas 11-15 (Box 263.3, Folder 4)
  - Buildings, General (Box 263.3, Folder 5)
  - By Buildings: A-B, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 6)
  - By Buildings: C-Cl, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 7)
  - By Buildings: Co-Cu, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 8)
  - By Buildings: D, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 9)
  - By Buildings: E, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 10)
  - By Buildings: F, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 11)
  - By Buildings: Ga, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 12)
  - By Buildings: Ge-Gi, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 13)
  - By Buildings: Ha, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 14)
  - By Buildings: He-Hi, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 15)
  - By Buildings: Ho, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 16)
  - By Buildings: I-J, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 17)
  - By Buildings: L, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 18)
  - By Buildings: Ma-Mo, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 19)
  - By Buildings: Mu, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 20)
  - By Buildings: N-O, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 21)
  - By Buildings: Par, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 22)
  - By Buildings: Park-Pars, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 23)
  - By Buildings: Sa-Se, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 24)
  - By Buildings: St-Su, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 25)
  - By Buildings: T, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 26)
  - By Buildings: W, 1938 (Box 263.3, Folder 27)
  - Plans, 1960 (Box 263.3, Folder 28)
  - Plans, 1960+ (Box 263.3, Folder 29)
  - Plans, 1963 (Box 263.3, Folder 30)
  - Plans and Notes, 1951-1969 (Box 263.3, Folder 31)
  - Kiosk, 1973 (Box 263.3, Folder 32)
- Campus
  - Back Campus, 1895-1983 (Box 264, Folder A)
  - General, 1947; 1994; 2000 (Box 264, Folder B)
  - Miscellaneous, 1899-1994 (Box 264, Folder C)
  - Front Campus, 1880's-1935 (Box 264, Folder 1)
  - Front Campus, 1970's-1990's (Box 264, Folder 2)
  - Hurricane, 1938 (Box 264, Folder 3)
  - Ice Storm, 1897 (Box 264, Folder 4)
  - Large Outside Bulletin Board, 1988 (Box 264, Folder 5)
  - Snow Scenes, 1891-1994 (Box 264, Folder 6)
- Capen Garden, 1970's-1990's (Box 264, Folder 7)
- Capen Garden - Mary Mattison van Schaik Tulip Garden, 1985-1997 (Box 264, Folder 7a)
- Central Heating System, 1946-1949; 1962 (Box 264, Folder 8)
- Chapin Lawn, 1967 (Box 264, Folder 9)
- College Lane, 1932 (Box 264, Folder 10)
- Dial Telephone, 1932-1961 (Box 264, Folder 11)
- Crosswalks (Box 264, Folder 12)
- Garden: Alice O. Smith Memorial Rhododendron Garden, 1983 (Box 264.1, Folder 1)
- Gates
  - College Hall Gates (Box 264.1, Folder 2)
  - College Lane Gates, 1966 (Box 264.1, Folder 3)
  - Green St. Gate, 1928-1995 (Box 264.1, Folder 4)
  - J. M. Greene, 1910-1993 (Box 264.1, Folder 5)
  - J. M. Greene - Individual photo (Box 264.1, Folder 6)
  - General Grounds Photographs, 1979-1994 (Box 264.1, Folder 7)
  - Grecourt Gates
    - Correspondence, 1922-1923 (Box 264.1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence- Brown, 1924 (Box 264.1, Folder 9)
    - Dedication, 1924 (Box 264.1, Folder 10)
    - Dedication- Invitations, 1924 (Box 264.1, Folder 11)
    - Dedication- Misc, 1924 (Box 264.1, Folder 12)
    - Dedication- Program, 1924 (Box 264.1, Folder 13)
    - Dedication- Speeches, 1924 (Box 264.1, Folder 14)
    - First Position, 1924-1953 (Box 264.1, Folder 15)
    - France (Box 264.1, Folder 16)
    - Grecourt Gates from College Hall, 1993 (Box 264.1, Folder 17)
    - Grecourt Gates from behind- Individual Photo, 1994 (Box 264.1, Folder 18)
    - Pictures, 1934-1977 (Box 264.1, Folder 19)
    - Photographs, 1924-1953 (Box 264.1, Folder 20)
    - Photographs- First Position, 1924-1953 (Box 264.1, Folder 21)
    - Photographs- First Position, 1924-1953 (Box 264.1, Folder 22)
    - Photographs, 1953- (Box 264.1, Folder 23)
- Hospital Hill (Box 264.1, Folder 24)
- Ivy, 1978; 1990 (Box 264.1, Folder 25)
- Japanese Garden, 1986-1999 (Box 264.1, Folder 26)
- Japanese Tea Garden: "The Japanese Tea Hut and Garden" by Mami Oyama, 1997 (Box 264.1, Folder 27)
- Japanese Tea Garden/Hut - Invoices, Memos, 1986 (Box 264.1, Folder 28)
- Lamont Bridge, 1930-1987 (Box 265, Folder 1)
- Lamont Bridge: Dedication, 1931; 1985 (Box 265, Folder 2)
- Lanning Fountain, 1911-1986 (Box 265, Folder 3)
- Lanning Fountain Photographs, 1912-1995 (Box 265, Folder 4)
- Lanning Fountain Restoration- Adam Jenkins Files, 1967-1998 (Box 265, Folder 5)
- Mill River, 1998 (Box 265, Folder 6)
- Orchard (Box 265, Folder 7)
- Outdoor Track and Field Facility, 1986; undated (Box 265, Folder 8)
- Paradise Road, 1989-1999 (Box 265, Folder 9)
- President's Garden, 1994; undated (Box 265, Folder 10)
- Pump, 1929 (Box 265, Folder 11)
- Sculpture, 1988-1992 (Box 265, Folder 12)
- Seats: Class of 1883 (Box 265, Folder 13)
- Sprinkler System (Box 265, Folder 14)
- State Hospital Property, 1916 -1917; 1997 (Box 265, Folder 15)
- Sun Dial, 1923; 1983; 1988 (Box 265, Folder 16)
- Trees, 1939-2000 (Box 265, Folder 17)
- Trees: Elms, 1900-1988 (Box 265, Folder 18)
- Vernon Street Lot, 1997- (Box 265, Folder 19)
- Paradise Pond (Box 266)
  - General, Clippings, 1952-2001 (Box 266, Folder 1)
  - Photographs: Banks, 1893-1986 (Box 266, Folder 2)
  - Photographs: Banks, 1891-1987 (Box 266, Folder 3)
  - Photographs: Boat House, 1919-1995 (Box 266, Folder 4)
  - Photographs: Boat House, 1900-1995 (Box 266, Folder 5)
  - Photographs: Dams, 1939-1986 (Box 266, Folder 6)
  - Photographs: Drained, 1952; 1960; 1981 (Box 266, Folder 7)
  - Photographs: General, 1889-1985 (Box 266, Folder 8)
  - Photographs: General, 1905-1989 (Box 266, Folder 9)
  - Photographs: Hoe Factory, 1884-1916 (Box 266, Folder 10)
  - Photographs: Individual Photo of Path by Paradise Pond, 1993 (Box 266, Folder 11)
  - Photographs: Island, 1880-1994 (Box 266.1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs: Islands, 1879-1958 (Box 266.1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs: President's House, 1950-1992 (Box 266.1, Folder 3)
- Smith College Campus Landscape Master Plan, 1994-1996 (Box 188.3)
- Index Seminum the Botanic Garden of Smith College, 1974/1975-1990/1991 (Box OV)
- Index Seminum the Botanic Garden of Smith College, 1991/1992-2000/2001 (Box OV)